<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the right worshipful the Deputy-Governour, and the Company of Merchants trading to the Levant-seas, at St Bartholemew-Exchange, May 1. 1689 By Edward Smyth, A.M. Fellow of Trinity-Colledge near Dublin; and preacher to the factory at Smyrna. Imprimatur, May 28. 1689. Hen. Wharton, R.R. in Christo P. ac D.D. Wilhelmo Archiep. Cant. à sacris domest.</title>
            <author>Smyth, Edward, 1665-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895976</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895976</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93340)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2371:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the right worshipful the Deputy-Governour, and the Company of Merchants trading to the Levant-seas, at St Bartholemew-Exchange, May 1. 1689 By Edward Smyth, A.M. Fellow of Trinity-Colledge near Dublin; and preacher to the factory at Smyrna. Imprimatur, May 28. 1689. Hen. Wharton, R.R. in Christo P. ac D.D. Wilhelmo Archiep. Cant. à sacris domest.</title>
                  <author>Smyth, Edward, 1665-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Sam. Crouch, at the corner of Pope's-Head-Ally, over-against the Royal Exchange in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata at the foot of the final page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXVI, 9 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153597:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the RIGHT WORSHIPFUL THE <hi>Deputy-Governour,</hi> AND THE Company of MERCHANTS Trading to the Levant-Seas, AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bartholemew-Exchange,</hi> May 1. 1689. By <hi>EDWARD SMYTH,</hi> A. M. Fellow of <hi>Trinity</hi>-Colledge near <hi>Dublin;</hi> And Preacher to the Factory at <hi>SMYRNA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>May</hi> 28. 1689.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IMPRIMATUR, </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Hen. Wharton,</hi> R.R. in Chriſto P. ac D.D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Archiep. <hi>Cant.</hi> à Sacris Domeſt.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Crouch,</hi> at the corner of <hi>Pope's-Head-Ally,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153597:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153597:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE GEORGE EARL of <hi>BERKELY,</hi> GOVERNOUR, AND THE Company of <hi>Turky</hi> Merchants.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following Diſcourſe has no other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to ſo Honourable a Dedication, but that your Command is the only reaſon it appears now in Print. Nor could any thing juſtifie the Publication of ſuch a Trifle, but that I reſolved to be wanting in no inſtance of an entire Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and that I would refuſe no opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of acknowledging to the World my Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the Honour of being elected into the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of ſo worthy a Society. to whoſe Induſtry and Ingenuity, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation in a great meaſure owes thoſe extraordinary Advancements
<pb facs="tcp:153597:3"/>of Wealth and Reputation abroad, this last Century has made. Whoſe most eminent Vertues, exemplary Charity, and ſignal Services to your Country, have rais'd you up to be the Ornament of your own, as the Envy of all neighbouring Nations. I could here offer a very just Apology for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>correctneſs of this Paper, that it was conceived and brought forth in haſte, that the Concern I had for my afflicted Brethren of <hi>Ireland,</hi> had ſo far the Aſcendant of my thoughts, as not to give way to that ſerenity and calmneſs of mind, which ſuch a performance did require. But ſince I addreſs my ſelf to Perſons of your Candour, I am not to doubt of all favourable allowances. I hope here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to glean ſomething in your own Harveſt, to which with leſs bluſhing I may prefix your Names. And as 'tis now my Duty, ſo ſhall it ever be my Study to promote your Proſperity and Happineſs, for obtaining which Bleſſings, ſhall be daily offer'd the Prayers of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Right Honourable, and Gentlemen, Your ever obliged, and moſt obedient Servant,</hi> EDWARD SMYTH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153597:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the <hi>Levant-Company.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ISAIAH <hi>XXVI. latter part of</hi> Ver. <hi>ix.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—For when thy Judgments are in the Earth, the Inhabitants of the World will learn Righteouſneſs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SO wonderful are the Methods by which the Divine Wiſdom has contrived our Salvation; that the bare conceiving them is no leſs above our Capacity, than that Infinite Reward ſurpaſſes all our Pretenſions to Merit. There is not one At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute in the Divinity, which bears not a part in the miraculous Work of our Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153597:4"/>the Unſpeakable Wiſdom invented it, and the Almighty Power accompliſhed it; his Mercy has provided for our Infirmities, and his Juſtice has inſured our Salvation, that our hope is not in vain in the Lord.</p>
            <p>And if ever Religion provided effectually for the ſalvation and happineſs of Mankind, this is peculiar to Chriſtianity. For if we have the leaſt ſpark of Ingenuity or Good Nature in our Temper, the Evangelical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſuited to the moſt prevailing Paſſions of our Soul, the Cords of Love, the Wings of Mercy, the Charms of Heaven, its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights drawn to the Life, the Voice of the Charmer, who ſurely Charms moſt wiſely; the Pleaſure of Religion, and the Sweets of Vertue muſt make us Proſelytes to Heaven, and force us to be Happy.</p>
            <p>But then, ſhould we deſpiſe even all theſe powerful Inducements to Happineſs, thô we are deaf to the Voice of the Charmer; the Long-ſuffering of God does not yet fail us. There are his terrible Judgments ſet out with all the Aggravations of Horrour and Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to reclaim us; to awaken us from that ſleep, which is ſurely unto Death, the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the Lord, the Flaming Sword, an
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153597:4"/>Angry God armed with Power, and Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance muſt ſtrike us into a religious reverence. <hi>When the Lion roareth who will not hear?</hi> Hoſ. 11.10. When the Almighty appears clad with his Robes of Vengeance, as the Prophet ſpeaketh, and ſurrounded with the Terrour of his Judgments making Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Sin, how ſhall the amazed ſinner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? with what confuſion of face muſt he loath his polluted Soul! If the ſtill Voice could not, the Eloquence of God ſpeaking in his Judgments muſt deeply affect him with the profoundeſt Dread and Reverence. Even the ſtupid <hi>Romans</hi> could then think of God, when Calamities were their ſevere Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers: <hi>For when thy Judgments</hi> (O Lord) <hi>are in the Land, the Inhabitants of the World will learn Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where, by Righteouſneſs, as is obvious in Scripture-Phraſe, we are to underſtand Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Religion in general: ſo that the ſence of the words will be this, That the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Judgments are moſt inſtructive of Duty and Religion; that this is their Drift, and that we ought to learn this Leſſon from them. From which words I will take occaſion to diſcourſe to the following Particulars.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153597:5"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>First,</hi> I will endeavour to Aſſign ſome Proper Marks, and Characters which may enable us to diſcern the Divine Judgments; as when diſpenſed by a Special Providence, and proceeding from the more immediate Hand of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I will enquire into the more Notorious Ends, to which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom has directed his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I will enquire, what is the Proper Behaviour of a Chriſtian under the Judgments of God, and what Influence they ought to have on our Lives.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>First</hi> then, I will endeavour to Aſſign ſome Proper Marks and Characters, which may enable us to diſcern the Divine Judgments; as when diſpenſed by a Special Providence, and proceeding from the Hand of God.</p>
            <p>To aſcribe every Petty Chance, that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, to a Special Providence, may ſignifie Lightneſs; to father on God the Miſchiefs ariſing from our Sin and Folly, may ſavour
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153597:5"/>of Prophaneneſs. By the Judgments of God therefore, I deſire you will underſtand ſuch extraordinary Occurrences, as carry in them ſome peculiar Marks of the Divine Anger; and are ſignal Inſtances of his Vindictive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>And here ſometimes the Hand of God is made bare, rais'd up, and ſtretch'd out in the Performance of moſt ſurprizing Works: Thus the Earth ſwallow'd up <hi>Corah</hi> with his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complices; and a Fire from Heaven ſnatched away the prophane hands, which offer'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe; and many ſuch ſignal Examples whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unaccountable from the Power or Efficacy of Natural Cauſes as to all their circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, do the Holy Scriptures afford us.</p>
            <p>But then again, that ſame Almighty Hand is wrapped up ſometimes in a complication with Inferiour Cauſes when 'tis not lifted up ſo high, or ſo far extended in miraculous Works. And here the ſpecial Vindictive Providence may not be impreſſed on Events, in Characters ſo big and clear, as to be legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the moſt prejudiced eye. The Tracts thereof may be ſometimes too fine and ſubtil, to be deſcried by a dimn ſight, with a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient glance, or upon a groſs view it may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153597:6"/>not affect the unreaſonable ſceptick, or ſuch as are wholly indiſpoſed to receive it.</p>
            <p>But ſhall not we adore his Almighty Power, and acknowledge his Judgments in inferiour Events, in a Plague or Famine unleſs a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Comet ſets the World on fire, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze us into a fit of Religion? muſt we wantonly preſcribe to the Divine Wiſdom? deny him the Miniſtry of Second Cauſes, and refuſe all Nouriſhment, unleſs we are fed with palpable Miracles? For thô Special Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the ſeverer diſpenſation of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is ſometimes clouded by the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Natural Agents, yet if we attend and conſider them, we ſhall eaſily diſcover ſome Marks of Vengeance imprinted on them. And ſurely 'tis the practice of good men, to contemplate and ſtudy Providence; the Prophet ranketh him only among the wiſe, who underſtandeth the Judgments of the Lord: 'tis a Matter for pious meditation, warranted by the practice of good men, to implore the manifeſtation of God's Power and Juſtice. If we therefore approach with this preparation of mind, ready to attend the leaſt intimations of his diſpleaſure, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them to the amendment of our Lives, to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153597:6"/>learn Righteouſneſs from them, the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Marks and Characters may be of good uſe to us, to diſcern and reverence the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: And theſe Characters I ſhall draw either from the Nature, or ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of ſuch Events.</p>
            <p>The firſt Character then of a Special Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and the viſible Hand of God, is the wonderful ſtrangeneſs of Events; as when great Effects are accompliſh'd, either by no apparent means, or by means wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionate, and often repugnant to the effect. Thus have we ſeen the mightieſt Forces diſcomfited; the firmeſt Structures demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Deſigns enforced, with all the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Strength and Cunning confounded and how unaccountable the way? no viſible means appear'd, Nature ſeeming to have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged the War, and the Elements to have fought againſt them: Panick Fears, or ſudden Deaths, having ſeized the principal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. How ready is any part of the Creation to miniſter to the Divine Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? the Stars in their courſes fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Siſera, Judges</hi> 5.20. the Winds and Skys became Auxiliaries to <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> the Lord thundred upon the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153597:7"/>how ſhould they ſtand againſt the Hoſt of Heaven? the Angel of the Lord went out, and ſmote in the Camp of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> 185000 Men. Thus the mighty Power of <hi>Antiochus</hi> was to be broken without hands.</p>
            <p>How often has Impotency, and the weak things of the Lord, triumphed over Might? Thus a Stripling, furniſhed only with the Breaſt-plate of Faith and a Pebble, ſhall fell down a monſtrous Gyant. thô armed with an Helmet of Braſs, a huge Target, Sword and Spear. How often have we ſeen the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Intrigue and Policy, whoſe Foundation was laid in Hell, either blaſted of it ſelf, or bafled by ſimplicity? the moſt perſpicacious Counſellours blinded and infatuated? the ſubtil, treacherous, deſigning Politician not only ſupplanted in his wicked enterprize, but diſmally chaſtiſed by it, and falling into his own ſnare? Surely then ſuch Occurrences do more than inſinuate the Divine Vengeance concerned to countermine and confound ſuch devices. 'Tis he certainly that <hi>maketh the Diviners mad, turneth wiſe Men backward, and maketh their knowledge fooliſh,</hi> Iſaiah 44.25. When Plots contrived in darkneſs are by unaccountable accidents diſcloſed and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153597:7"/>brought to light, a Bird of the Air telling the Matter, or the Stones crying out Treaſon, as the Prophet ſpeaketh: and ſhall not this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the Finger of God to be engaged? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that very deſign, which contrived the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>David,</hi> encreaſeth his Honour; the Stratagems to ſupplant <hi>Daniel,</hi> make him grow in the King's favour. Muſt not this then be the ſpecial Operation of that God whoſe peculiar it is to do wondrous things, to be terrible in his Judgments?</p>
            <p>A ſecond Character of a Special Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, is the ſeaſonableneſs and ſuddenneſs of Events.</p>
            <p>When pernicious Enterprizes, which aim at nothing leſs than the ſubverſion of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are grown to maturity, and are juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for execution, how often, beyond the Power of Humane Underſtanding, have we ſeen them either ſurpriſingly diſcovered, or ſeaſonably prevented? And ſhall not this be a pregnant evidence, that an ever-vigilant Eye, and the all-powerful Hand are enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? Thus was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with his Hoſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed, when he had juſt overtaken the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Thus when <hi>Sennacherib</hi> with an infinite force had inveſted <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153597:8"/>when certain death ſeem'd to threaten the holy City, <hi>God put a Hook into his Noſe, and turn'd him back into his own Land,</hi> 2 King. 9.28. When the prophane <hi>Caligula</hi> was juſt ready to diſcharge his bloody rage on the <hi>Jews,</hi> for their refuſing to worſhip the preſumptuous Wretch; a domeſtick Sword preſently gave vent to his revengeful Breath. When <hi>Julian,</hi> by his Authority and Policy, had projected the overthrow of our Religion, his Plot is bafled, and he falls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloriouſly by an unknown Hand. Certainly then we muſt here acknowledge the ſecret efficacy of God, who pours down ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Vengeance on the counſels of the wicked. This is the method of his peculiar Providence, he could as eaſily prevent the very beginning of wicked Deſigns; but he permits the Contrivers to mount to the top of Confidence and Expectation; and then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſurprizingly, unexpectedly he iſſues forth a Judgment, and confounds the Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Undertaking. Be aſtoniſh'd therefore and tremble all ye workers of Iniquity, and let the Lord be magnified in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153597:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another Character of the Divine Judgments, and of a ſpecial Providence in diſpenſing them, is from their kind and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, which often bear a ſignificant reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to thoſe ſins, for which they are infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Puniſhments (ſaith a Father) are the forced Off-ſpring of wilful Faults, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore carry the Complexions and Features of their Parents: And thus the ſin becomes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten legible in the Judgment, which is deſign'd to puniſh it, which provoked and wreſted it from Heaven. How often have we ſeen am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Confidence mourning in Diſgrace; Avarice curſed with Decay of Eſtate; the blaſphemous Throat torn out; the bloody Oppreſſor weltring in his own Blood, who but juſt now glutted in his Brothers; an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident which almoſt continually doth happen; ſo ſignal is the Revenge of Murder: the Treacherous betray'd; Places which prided themſelves in Wealth and Greatneſs, Power and Magnificence, now buried in Ruins, and more deſolate than the Wilderneſs. Surely ſuch Occurrences do point out, and judicate the Finger of God, they ſpeak plainly that they are his doings: by ſuch Actions he moſt evidently declares himſelf the Judge and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153597:9"/>of Mankind; <hi>Who directeth the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Divine Vengeance againſt Babylon, to take Vengeance upon her as ſhe hath done,</hi> Jer. 51.49.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding therefore any obſcurity or intricacy that may ſometimes appear in the courſe of Providence; as whether ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents proceed from the more immediate hand of God: if we conſider wiſely, with pious Attention, and a devout Heart; if with Minds pure from vain Prejudices, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Affections; the Marks, and Characters now aſſign'd, will be of good Uſe and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to us.</p>
            <p>We are too apt indeed to put off the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Reflections, and with the <hi>Philiſtin</hi> loves to queſtion whether this came by the Hand of God or not. But we may anſwer our ſelves by a cheaper Experiment than they did: If the Characters now aſſign'd could not direct us; our own Sins will tell us plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we have deſerved the Divine Judgments: and ſurely it were more uſeful for a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to make this Application, then wantonly to diſpute about the Nature of them.</p>
            <p>There are ſome who either through idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of humour, or an affectation to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153597:9"/>wiſe, have undertaken to arraign the Judgments of God; and to level them ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Events, and Natural Effects. With ſuch preſumption ſome have attempted to account for that General Deluge, which ſwept away all Mankind, except Eight Perſons, from Natural Cauſes. But ſurely theſe Men are more acted with a fondneſs of their new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, than by any zeal for Truth. For whoever but ſeriouſly reflects on all the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of that Event, muſt confeſs it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the power of Nature or Chance; and will condemn that Philoſophy as vain, which would advance ſuch Extravagancies.</p>
            <p>Having thus vindicated the Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſhewn them to you by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Marks and Characters. I proceed,</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, To enquire into the more notorious Ends and Purpoſes to which the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom has directed them.</p>
            <p>The firſt end then of the Divine Judgments is to proclaim God's Omnipotence, and aſſert the juſt Power of God over the World.</p>
            <p>And can we imagine a more pregnant E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of a reſiſtleſs and uncontroulable Power; for behold the Effects of his Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; the Pillars of Heaven aſtoniſhed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153597:10"/>and the Earth trembling with an awful Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: Nature agaſt, and the Hinges of the World ſhaking. And now ſurely we are not of ſo Gygantick ſtoutneſs, to ſtand void of Senſe and Fear, when Nature herſelf is in ſuch Pangs and Convulſions. Are not theſe ſuch Examples as carry Conviction with them? As raviſh a Religious Fear and Reverence from us. Can any thing be more inſtructive of the deepeſt Humility, and moſt profound Adoration. When we ſhall ſee Fate ſubmit to the Command of God, and Neceſſity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as variable as Chance: For lo he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Earth to reel to and fro, he pulleth down and buildeth up as it pleaſeth him.</p>
            <p>The proudeſt Monarchs, whom he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtileth Gods, how ſuddenly does he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay them with Duſt, leaſt their Spirits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come too much exalted. How eaſily does he bafle their moſt Elaborate Contrivances. Did not every thing we wear about us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim our weakneſs; the Divine Judgments could not fail to be a ſufficient Amulet againſt Pride. Are we able to defend our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the leaſt Calamity; when the weakeſt Creature comes armed with a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Heaven, the very Duſt of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153597:10"/>Earth, or but a Troop of inconſiderable Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts can overcome an <hi>Egypt;</hi> though her Wealth and Power were as boundleſs, as her Sins were provoking.</p>
            <p>Can any Man then reflect on the many Judgments of God, on thoſe aſtoniſhing Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his Indignation; and not preſently tremble and ſtand amazed. With what an awful Regard, with what profound Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt this fill our Minds. Are not theſe ſuch effectual Arguments of Almighty Power, as muſt raiſe us in the greateſt Security; thô all the Dalliances of Vice had enchanted us, thô the Lethargy of Sin had locked up our Reaſon and Conſideration, yet ſuch ſignal Examples muſt affect us: the moſt harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hearts, and even ſear'd Conſciences can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape ſome impreſſion: For ſhall not we attend, when even Heaven and Earth are ſummon'd to hear.</p>
            <p>Lord, how can we ſufficiently Adore thy Power, when we meditate on thy terrible Judgments: for behold any part of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, ſhall at thy Command become a moſt powerful Executioner of Vengeance. Let but the Sea open her proud Waves, (and 'tis thy word that reſtrains them) and ſhe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153597:11"/>may ſhut in the World, as ſhe once did the Hoſt of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Surely then our Minds muſt be ſtupified; we are aſleep even unto Death, if ſuch inſtances cannot awaken us, <hi>For by his Judgments he ſheweth himſelf, and lifteth himſelf up,</hi> Pſal. 94.1, 2. <hi>The Lord is known by the Judgments he executeth,</hi> Pſal. 9.16.</p>
            <p>If the ſeveral parts of the Creation diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play the ſeveral Attributes of God; if we may read his Power in the Firmament, and the Heavens declare it. In his Judgments certainly 'tis writ in the faireſt and largeſt Print; and here we muſt read it, thô all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arguments would paſs without obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. If the wiſer Heathens by Thought and Study, by Speculation and Philoſophy were able from conſidering the Works of Nature to conclude an All-powerful Being: How ſtrongly do his wonderful Judgments enforce this Truth, and exact from us the humbleſt Acknowledgments of Almighty Power.</p>
            <p>A ſecond end of the Divine Judgments is, to vindicate his Juſtice in the Adminiſtration of the World: for were Men ſuffered with Impunity to proceed in a courſe of Impiety;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153597:11"/>to enjoy the fruits of Rapine, Injuſtice, and other Vices, which then might appear gainful; were they ſuffer'd to defie Heaven with their crying ſins; this might ſeem to arraign the Juſtice of God; it might give the Atheiſts and Epicureans Objection ſome colour, that in the Adminiſtration of the World there was no regard had to the good and vertuous. But tho' this, if true, might be abundantly anſwer'd; that the Methods of Wiſdom, and Rules of Juſtice, by which the Almighty acts, do infinitely ſurpaſs our Capacities; either from the feebleneſs of our Reaſon, or finiteneſs of our Nature; and becauſe the Divine Adminiſtration has no compleat deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination here, but has regard to a future Judgment. Yet to the everlaſting terrour of wickedneſs, moſt ſignal Vengeance often o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertakes the wretched ſinner here; and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſins ſeldome eſcape ſome ſignal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or General Calamity. The Examples from Scripture, and ſuch as I have already aſſign'd; yea, the Occurrences of our own Age will ſufficiently confirm this.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Another end of the Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is, to work in us an entire hatred and deteſtation of ſin.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153597:12"/>
            <p>'Tis the greateſt force and provication to the Deity, when he pours down his wrath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, he does not willingly grieve us, or cauſleſly afflict us: 'Tis our ſins which makes us ſmart under that Hand, which otherwiſe would ſhowr down nothing but Bleſſings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. What ought our demeanour then to be, when Judgments are upon us, and we groan under the preſſure of Afflictions? Why to reflect on our ſins, to bluſh and be aſhamed; to be humbled for our Iniquities, which were the cauſe of that and all our ſufferings; aſſuring our ſelves, that whatever evil Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are in the Judgments and Afflictions which befal us, our ſins have ſet them all in motion.</p>
            <p>And when the Avenger is at the Gate, O how laſhing the folly, how confounding muſt the guilt of ſin appear? When <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Favourite of Heaven is led into Captivity for her crying Idolatry, how pungent muſt her Reſentments be? How afflicting the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of her Spiritual Fornications. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely blind and ſtupid therefore muſt we be, or monſtrouſly profane, if ſuch Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Divine Power and Vengeance do not awe us, and frighten us from ſin. 'Tis
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153597:12"/>our incurable folly that Afflictions are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effectual Phyſick of our Souls; that the bitter is the only Soveraign Potion.</p>
            <p>How muſt the wretched ſinner appear confounded; when he ſees Almighty God, whom but even now he openly affronted, whoſe Religion he ridicul'd, whoſe Honour he abuſed, coming on the Wings of Power, and making inquiſition for ſin; when there is an Earthquake ready to ſwallow him up, or a Fire from Heaven to conſume him. O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Miſcreant! Whither wilt thou fly from the All-ſeeing, or ſhelter thy ſelf from his preſence? Can Darkneſs ſcreen thee, or the Night cover thee? Abominate then thy ſins, loath thy polluted ſelf; Cut off the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of thy Deſtruction, which have rendered thee ſo obnoxious.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, Another end of the Divine Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is to beget in us a thorough Contempt of the World and its fatal Dalliances: to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Divine Precept of ſetting our Hearts on things above.</p>
            <p>For do not the Divine Judgments teach us; either how fugitive and uncertain, or how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfying and empty all ſublunary Beings are. How ſuddenly have we ſeen the adamantine
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153597:13"/>works of Art and Contrivance ſubverted. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Foundations of the World trembling, when the God of Nature was angry. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents the vain Eſſays to Eternity, rais'd to perpetuate the Memory of ſome remarkable Accident, or to carry the Name of ſome Great Perſon to late Poſterity, how often have we ſeen them buried in thoſe very Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines, which 'twas hoped they ſhould reſcue from Oblivion. The beſt eſtabliſhed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms have been overturned in a moment. Thoſe places which prided themſelves in their imaginary Security; and boaſted of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their Inhabitants, and whoſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants were fit to be Companions to Princes; how has a Fire from Heaven, or any other Creature able to do it, when commiſſioned from Heaven to deſtroy, ſwept them away? So that ſcarce their Names remain to reproach their Pride.</p>
            <p>Common Prudence does ſtrongly preſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us this obſervation, when every day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us of the great emptineſs and uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all worldly enjoyments. And did not the wiſe Heathens of old, from this very To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick raiſe themſelves to a brave and generous contempt of the World; what elſe was the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153597:13"/>Moral of that Chance, by which they belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all things here below to be governed: but that all things are ſubject to the ſame fleeting and uncertain condition. And tho' no Inſtrument of Vengeance were ſent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, no earthly thing is in itſelf durable; but ſhall return to its original corruption. And do not the Divine Judgments enforce this Duty from higher Conſiderations; when Deſtruction falls in like a mighty torrent. The rich Man but begins to enjoy, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that very Night his Soul is required from him. And this ſurely muſt correct our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, it muſt ſecure us from the Syren Enchantments of but momentary Evils. For as ſin is the laſting evil which has infected our Nature, ſo Judgment and Vengeance will always hang over us to frighten us from the gilded Poyſon, and wean us by frequent diſappointments from any fondneſs we may have for earthly things.</p>
            <p>Thus have I laid before you the more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Ends of the Divine Judgments, which are intended either to proclame the Power, or vindicate the Juſtice of God; to work in us a thorough hatred of ſin, and a generous contempt of all worldly things.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153597:14"/>
            <p>I proceed therefore in the third and laſt place, to enquire what is the proper behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of a Chriſtian under the Judgments of God, and what influence they ought to have on our Lives.</p>
            <p>Almighty God takes no delight in hurling the World into Confuſion, and turning Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties into Ruines, making whole Countries a a deſolation. Our provocations muſt cry aloud when he executes the ſeverity of his Judgments. 'Tis therefore for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin, and frightning us from it by ſuch dreadful Examples, by all the Rhetorick of the moſt amazing Inſtances, and all the Eloquence of the acuteſt Pain.</p>
            <p>To learn our Duty therefore in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, we are to reflect on all the Ends of the Divine Judgments already aſſign'd.</p>
            <p>Are the Divine Judgments then evidently declarative of an Almighty Power? This ſurely muſt imprint on us the profoundeſt Humility and moſt awful Reverence, it muſt affect us with all ſorts of Religious Fear: it muſt ſtrike into our Hearts the moſt ſincere dread of his ever glorious Majeſty; it muſt inflame us with the greateſt Acknowledgments, with the loudeſt Acclamations of the Infinite Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153597:14"/>of God, and his adorable Perfections; for ſhall not we fear, when the Heavens do ſhake and tremble. And in this Duty we have the devout <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>'s Zeal ſo ardent, that it muſt excite ours, and we ſhall cry out with one mouth: <hi>Men ſhall ſpeak of the might of thy terrible acts, and I will declare thy greatneſs. They ſhall ſpeak of the glory of thy kingdom, and talk of thy power.</hi> We muſt celebrate the adorable Perfections diſplayed in ſuch wonderful Events. Do not the Divine Judgments glorifie his Juſtice; and ſhall they not inſpire us to magnifie this glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, when his Judgments repreſent to us his ſignal Triumphs over Sin; all the Strength and Beauty of the World being made Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to the Grave, and Captives to Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which but juſt now bid him ſo proud a defiance. We who juſt now finned with as much Security and Confidence, as tho' we had blinded the Eyes, bugbear'd the Juſtice, or commands the Power of God; cannot, however, but applaud his Juſtice: when of a ſudden like one highly provoked he draws forth the Sword of his deſtroying Angel, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Wretch who looked ſo big into the Duſt, and hurls him into Deſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153597:15"/>
            <p>Are not the Divine Judgments ſent from Heaven to raiſe in us an hatred and averſion to ſin; and to wean us from the World. And ſurely the leaſt ſerious reflection on them cannot fail of this effect. When the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Vengeance are upon us, when Death in the ghaſtly appearance of a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtares us in the face; muſt we not then melt into ſuch Complaints as theſe: O that I had ſerved God as faithfully, as I have done the World, he would not have forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me, as that now is like to do. Had I laid up my Treaſure in Heaven, it would not have been in the power of any outward accident now to deprive me of him. If theſe Flames of Vengeance are ſo inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who ſhall be able to dwell with everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Burnings. Is it not the height of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to defie any longer, to provoke an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry God, infinitely more dreadful than this can be. Farewel then all ye deceitful Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; tho' I plac'd my Riches next my Heart, that could not clip their wings, or ſtop their flight. Thô I preſerved my Beauty with all the Extravagance of Art; I muſt loſe it this inſtant. Now I underſtand by dear Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thee and my ſelf better (O bewitching
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153597:15"/>World) then to fix my Happineſs any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger here. I will hereafter lay up my Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Heaven, I will be no longer cheated with imaginary good, but will make proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the true and everlaſting happineſs. Let theſe then be our reflections, and we ſhall riſe with greater Glory, our inward Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will outſhine whatever we could boaſt of outward ſplendor. We ſhall come out puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from the Fire of Afflictions; with our Souls poſſeſſed of the only valuable Riches of Grace and Vertue.</p>
            <p>Our proper demeanour then, and the uſe we are to make of the Divine Judgments, the moſt ſignal expreſſions of Almighty God's diſpleaſure is, what the Prophet in my Text draws from them, <hi>To learn Righteouſneſs,</hi> to be inſtructed in the Ways of Vertue, and in all the Duties of Religion.</p>
            <p>And is not this the Moral and Natural Conſequence of the Divine Judgments; which repreſent Sin in its proper Colours, attended with horrour and amazement, dread and confuſion of face. And when we ſee Vice thus ſinking into Hell, how much muſt we be enamoured with the Comlineſs, the Divine Pleaſure, the Heaven of Vertue,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153597:16"/>which the wretched Sinner only admires to aggravate his miſery. Can any thing more effectually recommend Humility, than the exemplary downfal of Pride; when a Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand from Heaven levels us with the Duſt, and forces the vain Bubble to an humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of his true Original, where the Worm is our Siſter, and a much happier Creature. When we ſee Luxury and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance chaſtiſed by ſome ſignal Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by the Deſolation of a Plague, by an Earthquake, by a Fire from Heaven: How effectually muſt this preſs upon our Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the contrary and proper Vertues of Sobriety and Temperance. All that deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful pleaſure and advantage with which ſin has ſo long impoſed on us, appears now in its Native Deformity, with its true Off-ſpring Vengeance and Judgment. With what zeal and ardency muſt we fly to the Breaſt-plate of Faith, when all our imaginary Security ſhall betray us, when neither Palaces nor Bulwarks can defend us; and the Earth finking under the load of our Iniquities cannot afford us footing. Shall not the Hypocrite then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold his Soul, when he ſees that all his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to Religion make him only the more
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153597:16"/>obnoxious to Vengeance, and that his Rags and Nakedneſs are now moſt apparent. Is there any thing then which makes us more effectually bow to the Precepts of Religion, then the Terrours of the Lord, then his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, his dreadful Judgments.</p>
            <p>Whence do we proceed better Proficients then from the School of Calamities. A ſtorm will inſpire Devotion even into that thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Wretch, who in his Security and Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery reviled every thing that was ſerious; who ſcorned to damp his Mirth with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy thoughts of Religion, and the ſad countenance of Sobriety. Who knew no ſuch thing as the Pleaſures of the Mind, and would not value whether he had any ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Faculties, unleſs it were for the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of Oaths, and making new Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the ways of wickedneſs; who was as great a Monſter in Morality as ever there was in Nature. How ſuppliant a Convert has a ſtorm made him, how has an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake reformed him. When the Angel of Vengeance is at hand, ready to ſmite the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and Oppreſſor; how does this melt him into love and kindneſs, into charity and good works; is he not ready to cloath the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153597:17"/>naked, whom he even now ſpoiled, and to relieve that poor man, whoſe Face he had now been grinding.</p>
            <p>Had moſt ſins no other puniſhment then there neceſſary and natural conſequents; were there no other ſcourge for Luxury and Intemperance, but decay of Eſtate, a Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Body, and that they ſow the Seeds of all Diſtempers, this would be Amulet againſt them to a conſidering Man. But when a flaming Sword, a Plague and Famine, and infinite other Inſtruments of a moſt terrible Vengeance do certainly attend them. O ſtupified Man! O monſtrous Security! If this will not awaken you and force you to Repentance. When your Cities lie in Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines, mourning in Duſt and Aſhes, becauſe you neglected this Duty; when your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try welters in Blood, and even the Stones cry out againſt you, to melt your more har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened Heart. You cannot behold ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation without making this reflection; 'Tis our ſins ſurely which have made us thus liable to the Divine Vengeance; had we any reaſon to expect his Protection, we might ſit quiet thô the World be overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; this was the Hedge about <hi>Job,</hi> which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153597:17"/>till withdrawn, bafled all the Attempts of Satan: But alas, our ſins have put a Bar to this Claim, we have forfeited God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and our reliance is now but preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption. And can any thing more effectually preſs upon us Vertue and Religion than ſuch Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>And truly few Men are ſo hardned, as not to be ſtruck with an awful Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to be forced into ſome Fit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; when they labour under ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Judgment: For Vengeance carries with it ſuch a convincing force, that few are able to reſiſt it: Even the Atheiſt cries to Heaven, when Death in the dreadful ſhape of a Judgment (to him ſurely moſt terrible) do ſeize him. Thunder forces <hi>Caligula</hi> to ſeek for ſhelter; even the hardned <hi>Pharaoh</hi> relents, when the Almighty iſſues forth his Inſtruments of Vengeance; when the Strength of <hi>Egypt</hi> is overpowred by a Locuſt; how does it extort from him the ungrateful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his own weakneſs, and forces him to fly to the Interceſſion of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But then, alas, we are all <hi>Pharaohs</hi> too in our ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ingratitude; the Religious temper ſeldom out-lives our Deliverance; thoſe convictions
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153597:18"/>and reflections uſually wear off, as the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intermits. When the Scene is ſhifted, and the ſucceeding Light has diſpelled the Cloud, we then unbend the Bow, let our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer thoughts disband, and return to our former Security. But this ſurely, as 'tis the greateſt Abuſe of the Divine Mercy in our Deliverance, ſo muſt it pull down an heavier Judgment upon us.</p>
            <p>'Tis our duty then, to treaſure up the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious memory of all our paſt Sufferings, and ſo to perpetuate the effects of them; that we may come out the purer from the Furnace, and not like the New Moon return with the ſame Spots, not to imbibe again thoſe ſtains of ſin, which have already rendred us ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to Divine Vengeance. And was it not for this reaſon, that the Chriſtian Church in all Ages has thought fit to Conſecrate cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Days of Humiliation, as ſure and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Remembrancers of the Divine Judgments, and her frequent Deliverances; leaſt by a ſhameful Ingratitude ſhe ſhould trample on and bury the Mercies of God in Oblivion. But methinks common Prudence ſhould direct us to this Practice, to beware of that Rod under which we have ſmarted, and to forſake thoſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153597:18"/>ſins which have ſo often expoſed us to Death and Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Many therefore are the Duties to which our Deliverance from paſt Calamities, and the conſideration of Judgments we have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, do oblige us.</p>
            <p>Firſt we muſt ever glorifie Almighty God with the Songs and Triumphs of our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, we muſt write our Deliverance not on Tables of Stone, but on the fleſhly Tables of our Heart. <hi>The Righteous ſhall be glad in the Lord.</hi> When he ſees his Glory ſo conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly advanced, and his holy Perfections ſo illuſtriouſly ſhining through his Judgments; this ſignal conviction of Infidelity, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Prophaneneſs how does it confirm his Faith, and cheriſh his Hope. The juſt ſhall rejoyce, and all iniquity ſhall ſtop her mouth. How exceeding the Comfort? How triumphant is the Joy, when we receive ſo clear Pledges of God's Love and Favour to us, expreſs'd in his moſt tender Care over us, in protecting us from moſt imminent Dangers, and contriving our deliverance from ſuch ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Judgments; for were we not ſaved even as by Fire, and as Fire-brands pluckt out of the burning. Let us then ever magnifie (O
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153597:19"/>Lord) thy infinite Mercy's the only cauſe of our deliverance, for this was our Sanctuary and Refuge, it was not our own Skill and Counſel, not our Strength and Induſtry that ſaved us; but thou art our mighty Deliverer.</p>
            <p>A Second Duty incumbent on us, is often to meditate on paſt Judgments. We muſt not barely remember them, for this is no Vertue; but we muſt remember them with thoſe very paſſions of mind, thoſe ardent thoughts, affections, and reſentments we had when we ſuffered under them, and they were ſo viſible before us; what indignation, and reſolution we then expreſſed againſt ſin; what ſubmiſſions were then wrought in us to his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty pleaſure, and with what mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſelf-denyal we reſigned our ſelves. And this is remembring in Scripture phraſe, by which we may ſecure to our ſelves all the advantages of paſt afflictions, without the ſting and miſery which attends them; by ſetting them in a clear light before us, and making them preſent to us by a lively remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, ſo that they may be a conſtant bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to us againſt Vice. Let not thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Devotion expire, thoſe ſtruglings of the Spirit ceaſe, which burnt them ſo bright;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153597:19"/>if our Petitions kept equal pace with our Pain, let them do ſo with the remembrance of it now.</p>
            <p>Our Meditations on paſt Judgments ought alſo to beget in us a well grounded hope, and ſtrong confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The Lord hath delivered me, therefore he will deliver; I have often experimented his Mercy, therefore I will now fly to it. If we have ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our Prayers in the day of our Calamity, by any extraordinary Vow, or Sacred Promiſes (according to the pious Examples of Holy Men) we are now care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to perform them, and to releaſe that ſtrict Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation we have put our Souls under.</p>
            <p>And there are many other Religious Duties of the ſame nature (for there are ſcarce any which it does not confirm and encreaſe) which the remembrance of paſt Judgments ſtrongly recommend to our practiſe. Nothing can more effectually ſecure to us all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and fruits of the Spirit. But not having time now to enlarge on them, I muſt refer them to your own application.</p>
            <p>Only let me beg your attention, whilſt in a few words, I remind you of that late ſignal Judgment, and deplorable Calamity; in which this Honourable Audience was deeply wounded. The late Judgment which befel <hi>Smyrna,</hi> that complicated Calamity of an Earthquake moſt terrible in all its circumſtances, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by a Fire, (too pregnant an inſtance of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance) cannot, if barely related, but fill the moſt hardned Heart with pity and aſtoniſhment; but on you ſurely, whoſe misfortune it was to be too much concerned in it, who were ſo great Sufferers in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation it wrought, it ought, it muſt make, a more deep and laſting impreſſion.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153597:20"/>
            <p>The Lord ſurely was in the Earthquake, and in the Whirlwind; the ſuddenneſs of the Deſtruction even exceeding thought, and all the diſmal circumſtances at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending this Accident are too ſtrong an evidence, that the deſtroying Angel came from Heaven, and that the Almighty put on Vengeance to the overthrow of that miſerable City.</p>
            <p>For behold the trembling Earth ſinking to her Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with the ſtroaks of God's Anger legible in her face; behold a great and opulent City, famous in ancient and ſacred Annals, and even then reſtored to her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Grandeur, ſurpaſſing in Trade, and equal in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other advantages to any of her Siſters in the <hi>East,</hi> reduced to ruin in a moment. The ſame inſtant ſaw her a moſt flouriſhing City, and an heap of Rubbiſh. And that nothing of her Beauty or Greatneſs might be legible in her Fall; a conſuming Fire devours her very Bowels, what eſcaped the Earthquake becomes a prey to the Fire. So heavy was the Hand of Heaven that it purſues her to the very Grave, buries her very Ruins, and razes her Foundation. O the conſternation of her living, and confuſion of her periſhing Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants! O the ſighs and tears, frights and amazements! O the deaths! (and many were deny'd even this mercy) O the half Deaths (Heads and Hearts miſerably ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving the other Members) of Men, Women, and Children lamenting, yet unable to help themſelves and one another! The Mother juſt lived to ſee her Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghter die, and the ſame Ruin involved the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. Such, had I courage, and were I ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to proceed in the deſcription, you may imagine the lamentable Condition of <hi>Smyrna</hi> was. <hi>And was this done upon the earth, and the Lord hath not done it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153597:20"/>
            <p>How ſwift (O Lord) is deſtruction, when thou doſt give it Commiſſion. Even the dull Earth ſhall become a ſwift Executioner of Divine Vengeance. One Inſtant can, and did overturn the Toil, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of an Age. Such is the folly and guilt of our ſins, that againſt a City ſo advantaged, ſo culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, ſo bleſſed, they can extort the heavieſt Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, even from that hand whence all her Bleſſings derived. It was from their fatal influence that ſhe is now forced to ſucceed in the Fate and Ruine, as in the Wealth and Splendour of her Neighbours; that ſhe is now become <hi>like unto Sodom and Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were that City able to ſpeak out of its Ruins; how Eloquent would ſhe be on that Subject of her Sufferings; what heavy Complaints would ſhe make againſt thoſe Sins which have been the certain and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Inſtruments of her deſtruction. Let her Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches then, let her Ruins and Deſolation ſpeak; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the genuine Off-ſpring of Vice, the fruit of thoſe things of which we ought to be aſhamed. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we cannot look on her Ruins but we muſt repent, we cannot ſee her miſeries without bewailing our own ſins. And let us not here flatter our ſelves, or run into that dangerous miſtake; that the Infidelity of the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Mahometan,</hi> that the Idolatry and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of <hi>Popery</hi> are the only provocations which brought down this heavy Judgment. Our ſins, alas, are but too much the ingredients, and its wounds and ſcars yet bleeding afreſh, are but too ſtrong an intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that we are ſtill in our ſins.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153597:21"/>
            <p>To conclude all then:</p>
            <p>You have heard how Eloquent the Judgments of the Lord are to perſwade Repentance, and inforce all the Duties of Religion; how they recommend Vertue from the ſtrongeſt Topicks of worldly Intereſt and Pleaſure, as the ſureſt means to preſerve both. How they repreſent to us moſt ſenſibly the deſtructive na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Sin, that all the Miſery and Unhappineſs which befals Mankind, flow certainly from this Fountain. This being then our caſe, common prudence, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious conſideration of our own advantage muſt direct us to that Duty which Chriſtianity commands. Sin and Folly will be found but two Names for the ſame thing. Let us therefore apply our ſelves to the ſtudy of true Wiſdom. Let us make the true advances in Grace and Vertue. And now the Judgments of the Lord are upon the Earth. Let us learn, let us practiſe Righteouſneſs, for Godlineſs we ſee is the true Gain, it has the Bleſſings of this World, and that which is to come.</p>
            <p>To which place of everlaſting Happineſs, Almighty God of his infinite Mercy, bring us all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. laſt line, after view a Full Stop. p. 11. l. 24. judicate r. indicate. p. 12. l. 17. loves r. Lords. p. 16. l. 14. would r. ſhould. p. 23. l. 23. bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear'd r. bribed. l. 22. commands r. commanded. p. 24. l. 13. Treaſure r Treaſures. l. 15. him. r. them. p. 29. l. 17. do r. does.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
